<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-softwire-map-dhcp-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MAP DHCPv6 Options">DHCPv6 Options for configuration of
    Address and Port Softwire CEs</title>

    <author fullname="Tomasz Mrugalski" initials="T." surname="Mrugalski">
      <organization abbrev="ISC">Internet Systems Consortium,
      Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>950 Charter Street</street>

          <city>Redwood City</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94063</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 650 423 1345</phone>

        <email>tomasz.mrugalski@gmail.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.isc.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <!-- Med and Xiaohong requested to be removed from the authors list
      <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
	  <street></street>
          <city>Rennes</city>
          <code>35000</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mohamed.boucadair@gmail.com</email>
	<uri>http://www.francetelecom.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>-->

    <author fullname="Xiaohong Deng" initials="X." surname="Deng">
      <!-- <organization></organization> -->

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6 Cordelia St.</street>

          <code>QLD 4101</code>

          <city>South Brisbane</city>

          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+61 3858 3128</phone>

        <email>dxhbupt@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ole Troan" initials="O" surname="Troan">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Telemarksvingen 20</street>

          <city>Oslo</city>

          <code>N-0655</code>

          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ot@cisco.com</email>

        <uri>http://cisco.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Congxiao Bao" initials="C.X." surname="Bao">
      <organization abbrev="Tsinghua University">CERNET Center/Tsinghua
      University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Room 225, Main Building, Tsinghua University</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100084</code>

          <country>CN</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+86 10-62785983</phone>

        <email>congxiao@cernet.edu.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wojciech Dec" initials="W" surname="Dec">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>The Netherlands</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>wdec@cisco.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Leaf Y. Yeh" initials="L." surname="Yeh">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Shenzhen</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>P. R. China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>leaf.yeh.sdo@gmail.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <!-- Qiong Sun requested joining author team as well (22.10.2011 12:10) -->

    <date />

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>Softwire WG</workgroup>

    <keyword>MAP</keyword>

    <keyword>DHCPv6</keyword>

    <!--  SECTION 0:  Abstract                      -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies DHCPv6 options, termed Softwire46 options,
      for the provisioning of Softwire46 Customer Edge (CE) devices.
      Softwire46 is a collective term used to refer to architectures based on
      the notion of IPv4 Address+Port for providing IPv4 connectivity across
      an IPv6 network, as specified by the IETF Softwires WG.</t>

      <t></t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!--  SECTION 1:  Introduction                  -->

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>A number of architectual solution proposals formed in the IETF
      Softwires Working Group use Address and Port (A+P) as their technolgy
      base in providing IPv4 connectivity service to end users using CE
      devices across a service provider's IPv6 network, while allowing for
      shared or dedicated IPv4 addressing of the CEs. This document specifies
      DHCPv6 options for the provisioning of such Softwire46 A+P based
      Customer Edge (CE) devices.</t>

      <t>An example of such a proposal is that of Mapping of Address and Port
      (MAP) defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>. The MAP
      solution architecture consists of one or more MAP Border Relay (BR)
      routers, responsible for stateless forwarding between a MAP IPv6 network
      domain and external public IPv4 network, and one or more MAP Customer
      Edge (CE) routers, responsible for forwarding between a user's private
      IPv4 network and the MAP IPv6 network domain. Collectively the MAP CE
      and BR form a domain when configured with common service paramaters.
      This characteristic is common to all of the Softwire46 proposals.</t>

      <t>To function in such a domain, a CE requires to be provisioned with
      the appropriate A+P service paramaters for that domain. This consists
      primarliy the IPv4 address the CE should use and the transport layer
      port-range(s), both of which may be derived from the CE's IPv6 prefix,
      as well as the port-indexing method. Furthermore the IPv6 transport mode
      (e.g. encapsulation or translation) also needs to be specified. In
      networks with a numerous number of CEs it is not feasible to configure
      these parameters manually on each CE, which forms the requirement for a
      dynamic provisioning mechanism using DHCPv6 <xref
      target="RFC3315"></xref> options that are the subject of this document.
      The means of configuration of the domain's gateway, e.g. the MAP BR, is
      outside the scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <!--  SECTION 2: REQUIREMENTS LANGUAGE                                         -->

    <section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="description" title="Softwire46 Service Information">
      <t>The following presents the information parameters that are used to
      configure a Softwire46 CE:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A Default Mapping Rule (DMR). This rule governs the default
          forwarding behaviour of the CE, ie it informs the CE of the gateway
          router's address or prefix that is to be used as a default transit
          gateway. The DMR is a mandatory rule for a CE. The presence of an
          address or prefix indicates the use of encapsulation or translation
          modes respectively.</t>

          <t>A Basic Mapping Rule (BMR). This rule governs the A+P
          configuration of the CE, including that of completing the CE's MAP
          IPv6 address, as well as deriving the CEs IPv4 address and port
          range(s). Key parameters of a BMR include: i) The IPv4 Prefix - Used
          to derive the CE's IPv4 address; ii) The Embedded Address bit length
          - Used to derive how many, if any, of the CE's IPv6 address is
          mapped to the IPv4 address. iii) The IPv6 prefix - used to determine
          the CE's IPv6 MAP domain prefix that is to form the base for the
          CE's MAP address. The BMR is an optional rule for a CE.</t>

          <t>A Forward Mapping Rule (FMR). This rule governs the MAP CE-CE
          forwarding behaviour for IPv4 destinations covered by the rule. The
          FMR is effectively a special type of an BMR, given that it shares
          exactly the same configuration parameters, except that these
          parameters are only applied for setting up forwarding. Its presence
          enables a given CE to communicate directly in "mesh mode" with other
          CEs. The FMR is an optional rule, and the absence of such a rule
          indicates that the CE is to use its default mapping rule for all
          destinations, i.e. operate in hub and spoke mode.</t>

          <t>Additional parameters. The specification allows flexibility in
          the level of automation a CE uses to derive its transport layer
          port-ranges, ranging from full derivation of this parameter from the
          CE's IPv6 prefix, to full parametrization of configuration
          independent of the CE's IPv6 prefix. Additional parameters such as
          the PSID allow this flexibility for CE's using the MAP algorithm.
          Paramaters fitting other port allocation algorithms are intended to
          be added in future revisions of this document. </t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <!--                                                  -->

    <section title="DHCPv6 Softwire46 Options">
      <t>The DHCPv6 protocol is used for Softwire46 CE provisioning following
      regular DHCPv6 notions, with the CE assuming the role of a DHCPv6
      client, and the DHCPv6 server providing options following typical DHCPv6
      server side policies. The format and usage of the options is defined in
      the following sub-sections.</t>

      <!-- <t>Discussion: Proposed layout assumes that several simple
      options are used. Such approach simplifies implementation as it
      is much easier for implementors to reuse existing code handling
      such options. This design choice comes at a cost,
      however. Clients must perform checks if provided set of options
      is complete. Alternatively, it would be possible to define one
      complex option that contains all mandatory
      parameters. </t> -->

      <t>A DHCPv6 server that is enabled to provision requesting CE's with
      Softwire46 options MUST include exactly one OPTION_S46 option in a REPLY
      message for each MAP domain the CE is determined to be part of - by
      default this is one domain. </t>

      <section anchor="what-where" title="Softwire46 Options Cardinality">
        <t>When requested by clients by means of an DHCPv6 Option Request
        Option a server SHOULD return one Softwire46 Container Option for each
        Softwire46 domain that a given CPE is determined to belong to.
        Typically a CE will belong to only one domain. Furthermore, multiple
        CEs can be part of a single domain, and thus share their Softwire46
        service domain configuration. The means of determing the domain of a
        CPE by is following typical DHCPv6 server policies and is not
        specified by this document.</t>

        <t>A returned Softwire46 Container Option MUST include exactly one DMR
        Rule option. It also MAY include zero or more other Rule Options.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="option-map" title="Softwire46 Container Option">
        <t>This MAP Container Option specifies the container used to group all
        rules and optional port parameters for a specified domain.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="img-map-option"
                title="MAP Container Option">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        OPTION_S46             |         option-length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+            encapsulated-options (variable length)             .
.                                                               .
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
	]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: OPTION_S46 (TBD1)</t>

            <t>option-length: 1 + Length of encapsulated options</t>

            <t>encapsulated-options: options associatied with this Softwire46
            domain.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The encapsulated options field encapsulates those options that are
        specific to this MAP Option. Currently there are three options that
        MAY appear here: OPTION_S46_RULE, OPTION_S46_DMR and
        OPTION_S46_PORTPARAMS. Other options suitable for a domain may be
        defined in the future. A DHCP message MAY include multiple S46
        Container Options (representing multiple domains), but typically it
        will have only one.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="S46 Rule Option">
        <t>Figure <xref target="img-option-rule"></xref> shows the format of
        the S46 Rule option used for conveying the BMR and FMR.</t>

        <t>A server MAY send more than one S46 Rule Option, if it is
        configured to do so. Clients MUST NOT send a S46 Rule Option.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="img-option-rule"
                title="S46 Rule Option">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        OPTION_S46_RULE        |         option-length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  prefix4-len  |               rule-ipv4-prefix                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| (continued)   |     ea-len    |  rule-flags  |  prefix6-len   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       rule-ipv6-prefix                        |
|                       (variable length)                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.             encapsulated-options (variable length)            .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: OPTION_S46_RULE (TBD2)</t>

            <t>option-length: length of the option, excluding option-code and
            option-length fields, including length of all encapsulated
            options, expressed in bytes.</t>

            <t>prefix4-len: 8 bits long field expressing the bit mask length
            of the IPv4 prefix specified in the rule-ipv4-prefix field. Valid
            values 0 to 32.</t>

            <!-- tomek todo: Do we want to restrict values to 0-32 here? -->

            <t>rule-ipv4-prefix: a fixed length 32 bit field that specifies
            the IPv4 prefix for the S46 rule.</t>

            <t>ea-len: 8 bits long field that specifies the Embedded-Address
            (EA) bit length. Values allowed range from 0 to 48.</t>

            <t>rule-flags: 8 bits long field carrying flags applicable to the
            rule. The meaning of specific bits is explained in <xref
            target="img-rule-flags"></xref>.</t>

            <t>prefix6-len: 8 bits long field expressing the bit mask length
            of the IPv6 prefix specified in the rule-ipv6-prefix field.</t>

            <t>rule-ipv6-prefix: a variable length field that specifies the
            IPv6 domain prefix for the S46 rule. The field is padded with
            follow up zero bits up to the nearest octet boundary when
            prefix6-len is not divisible by 8.</t>

            <t>encapsulated options: a variable field that may contain zero or
            more options that specify additional parameters for this S46
            BMR/FMR rule. Currently there are no such options defined, but
            they may be defined in the future.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The Format of the S46 Rule Flags field is:<figure align="center"
            anchor="img-rule-flags" title="S46 Rule Flags">
            <preamble></preamble>

            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Reserved     |F| 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Reserved: 7-bits reserved for future use as flags.</t>

            <t>F-Flag: 1 bit field that specifies whether the rule is to be
            used for forwarding (FMR). 0x0 = This rule is NOT used as a FMR.
            0x1 = This rule is also a FMR.</t>

            <t>Note: BMR rules can be also FMR rules by setting the F flag.
            BMR rules are determined by a match of the Rule-IPv6-prefix
            against the CPE's prefix(es).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>It is expected that in a typical mesh deployment scenarios, there
        will be a single DMR and a single BMR, which could also be designated
        as an FMR using the F-Flag.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="S46 DMR Option">
        <t>S46 DMR Option is used to convey values for Default Mapping Rule.
        S46 DMR Option MUST appear in each S46 Container Option and MUST NOT
        appear in the DHCP message directly. Figure <xref
        target="img-option-dmr"></xref> shows the format of the MAP Rule
        option used for conveying a DMR.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="img-option-dmr"
            title="S46 DMR Option">
            <preamble></preamble>

            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        OPTION_S46_DMR         |         option-length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|dmr-prefix6-len|            dmr-ipv6-prefix                    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+           (variable length)                   |
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.            encapsulated-options (variable length)             .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: OPTION_S46_DMR (TBD3)</t>

            <t>option-length: 1 + length of dmr-ipv6-prefix + encapsulated
            options, specified in bytes.</t>

            <t>dmr-prefix6-len: 8 bits long field expressing the bit mask
            length of the IPv6 prefix specified in the dmr-ipv6-prefix
            field.</t>

            <t>dmr-ipv6-prefix: a variable length field that specifies the
            IPv6 prefix or address for the S46 BR. This field is padded with
            follow up zeros to the nearest octet boundary when dmr-prefix6-len
            is not divisible by 8.</t>

            <t>encapsulated options: nested options associatied to this S46
            DMR option. Currently there are no such options defined, but they
            may be defined in the future.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="option-portparams"
               title="S46 MAP Port Parameters Option">
        <t>The Port Parameters Option specifies optional Rule Port Parameters
        that MAY be provided as part of the Mapping Rule for CEs using the MAP
        algorithm. It MAY appear as encapsulated option in OPTION_S46 option.
        It MUST NOT appear directly in a message. It MUST NOT appear (as a
        sub-option) in OPTION_S46_RULE nor OPTION_S46_DMR options. </t>

        <t>See <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>, Section 5.1 for
        detailed description of MAP algorithm that explains meaning of all
        parameters.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="img-option-portparams"
                title="S46 Port Parameters Option">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     OPTION_S46_PORTPARAMS     |         option-length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   offset      |    PSID-len   |              PSID             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: OPTION_S46_PORTPARAMS (TBD4)</t>

            <t>option-length: 4</t>

            <t>offset: (PSID offset) 8 bits long field that specifies the
            numeric value for the S46 algorithm's excluded port range/offset
            bits (A-bits), as per section 5.1.1 in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>. Allowed values are between
            0 and 16, with the default value being 4.</t>

            <t>PSID-len: Bit length value of the number of significant bits in
            the PSID field. (also known as 'k'). When set to 0, the PSID field
            is to be ignored. After the first 'a' bits, there are k bits in
            the port number representing valid of PSID. Subsequently, the
            address sharing ratio would be 2^k.</t>

            <t>PSID: Explicit 16-bit (unsigned word) PSID value. The PSID
            value algorithmically identifies a set of ports assigned to a CE.
            The first k-bits on the left of this 2-octets field is the PSID
            value. The remaining (16-k) bits on the right are padding
            zeros.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>When receiveing the Port Parameters option with an explicit PSID,
        the client MUST use this explicit PSID in configuring its MAP
        interface.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Usage of flags and paramaters">
      <t>The defined MAP options contain a number of flags and parameters that
      are intended to provide full flexibility in the configuration of a MAP
      CE. Some usage examples are:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A MAP CE receiving an OPTION_S46_DMR with a dmr-prefix6-len
          prefix length of 128, will assume an encapsulation mode [RFC2473] of
          IPv6 transport for the domain, e.g. [MAP-E]. Conversely, when the
          received option has a prefix length shorter than 128, the CE will
          assume a stateless NAT46 translation mode of IPv6 transport for the
          domain, e.g. [MAP-T].</t>

          <t>The presence of a OPTION_S46_RULE option, along with IPv4 prefix
          parameters, indicates to the CE that NAPT44 mode of operation is
          expected, following the address mapping rules defined in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>. Conversely, the absence of
          an OPTION_MAP_RULE option indicates that NAT44 mode is not required,
          and that the MAP CE is to plainly encapsulate (MAP-E mode) or
          statelessly translate using NAT64 (MAP-T mode) any IPv4 traffic sent
          following the DMR.</t>

          <t>The MAP domain ipv6-prefix in the BMR should correspond to a
          service prefix assigned to the CPE by the operator, with the latter
          being assigned using regular IPv6 means, e.g. DHCP PD <xref
          target="RFC3633"></xref> or SLAAC. This parameter allows the CPE to
          select the prefix for MAP operation.</t>

          <t>The EA_LEN parameter, along with the length of the IPv4 prefix in
          the BMR option, allows the MAP CE to determine whether address
          sharing is in effect, and what is the address sharing ratio. Eg: A
          prefix4-len of 16 bits, and EA-len of 18 combines to a 32 bit IPv4
          address with a sharing ratio of 4.</t>

          <t>The use of the F(orward) flag in the BMR allows a CE to apply a
          received BMR as an FMR, thereby enabling mesh-mode for the domain
          covered by the BMR rule.</t>

          <t>In the absence of a BMR, the presence of the mandatory DMR
          indicates to the CPE the address or prefix of a BR, and makes the
          MAP CE fully compatible with DS-Lite and stateful or stateless NAT64
          core nodes. Eg a MAP CE configured in MAP-E mode, with just a DMR
          and a BR IPv6 address equivalent to that of the AFTR, effectively
          acts as a DS-Lite B4 element. For more discussion about MAP
          deployment considerations, see <xref
          target="I-D.mdt-softwire-map-deployment"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="DHCPv6 Server Behavior">
      <t><xref target="RFC3315">RFC 3315 Section 17.2.2</xref> describes how a
      DHCPv6 client and server negotiate configuration values using the ORO.
      As a convenience to the reader, we mention here that a server will by
      default not reply with a MAP Rule Option if the client has not
      explicitly enumerated it on its Option Request Option.</t>

      <t>A Server following this specification MUST allow the configuration of
      one or more MAP Rule Options, exactly one DMR Option and optional Port
      Parameters Option and SHOULD send such options grouped under a single
      MAP Container Option.</t>

      <t>Server MUST include a MAP Container Option (which encapsulates all
      MAP Rule, MAP DMR, and MAP Port parameters Options) in its responses if
      client requested it using OPTION_MAP in client's Option Request Option
      (ORO).</t>

      <t>Server MAY include more than one MAP Container Options only in the
      unlikely case of having more than one MAP Domain configured.</t>

      <!-- sadly, with introduction of OPTION_PORTPARAMS that is no longer true.
      <t>Rules assignment is a stateless process from the server's
      perspective. Server does not need to maintain a state of rules
      provisioned to clients, track lifetimes, expire outdated rules
      etc. Server SHOULDs assign the same set of rules to all CEs in
      one MAP Domain, unless there are several classes of CEs defined,
      e.g. regular and premium users. In such case, each class of CEs
      is expected to get the same set of rules. Server is not expected
      to track MAP rules on a per CE basis. Exact assignment of
      specific rules to a specific CEs is outside of scope of this
      document.</t> -->

      <t>The server SHOULD be capable of following per client assignment rules
      when assigning MAP options.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DHCPv6 Client Behavior">
      <t>A S46 CE acting as DHCPv6 client will request MAP configuration to be
      assigned by the DHCPv6 server located in the IPv6 network. Such a client
      SHOULD request OPTION_S46 option in its ORO in SOLICIT, REQUEST, RENEW,
      REBIND and INFORMATION-REQUEST messages. </t>

      <t>When processing received S46 options the following behaviour is
      expected:<list style="symbols">
          <t>A client MUST support processing multiple received
          OPTION_S46_RULE options in a container OPTION_S46 option</t>

          <t>A client receiving an unsupported S46 option, or an invalid
          parameter value SHOULD discard that OPTION_S46 and log the
          event.</t>

          <t>Exactly one OPTION_S46_DMR is allowed per OPTION_MAP option.
          Client MUST ignore the entire OPTION_MAP if there is zero or more
          than one S46 DMR Option.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Clients using the MAP algorithm, which determines the service
      interface and port-set, MUST be capable of applying the received S46
      option parameters for the configuration of the local MAP service: The
      DMR, as well as BMR and FMR options when present, MUST be used to
      configure the CE's MAP service characteristics as per Section 5 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref></t>

      <t>Note that system implementing CE functionality may have multiple
      network interfaces, and these interfaces may be configured differently;
      some may be connected to networks that call for MAP, and some may be
      connected to networks that are using normal dual stack or other means.
      The CE system should approach this specification on an
      interface-by-interface basis. For example, if the CE system is MAP
      capable and is attached to multiple networks that provide the MAP
      Mapping Rule Option, then the CE system MUST configure a MAP service
      (i.e. a translation or encapsulation) for each interface separately as
      each MAP provides IPv4 connectivity for each distinct interface. Means
      to bind a MAP configuration to a given interface in a multiple
      interfaces device are out of scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Deployment considerations">
      <t>The usage of the S46 Option(s) is intended for statelss server
      operation, whereby for a given CE client, the server maintains no state
      other than configuration regarding the S46 options that are sent to the
      client. The usage of the Port Option in particular requires a server
      configuration that allows a unique S46 option to be offered to each
      client, i.e. use of a per client option repository such as LDAP. </t>

      <t>In a typical environment, there will be only one MAP domain, so
      server will provide only a single instance of MAP Option(s) to all
      clients in that domain.</t>

      <t>In case of multiple provisioning domains, as defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-homenet-arch"></xref>, one server may be required to
      provide information about more than one MAP domain. In such case it is
      envisaged that the server will provide two or more instances of MAP
      Container Options, each with its own set of encapsulated options that
      define MAP rules for each specific MAP domain. Details of mulitple
      provisioning domains are discussed in Section 4.1 of <xref
      target="I-D.mdt-softwire-map-deployment"></xref>. Such a deployment is
      outside of scope for this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="example" title="S46 Options Examples">
      <t>DHCPv6 server provisioning a single MAP Rule to a CE (DHCPv6 client)
      will convey the following MAP options in its messages:</t>

      <section title="BMR Option Example">
        <figure align="center" anchor="img-bmr-example"
                title="BMR Option Example">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
TODO: Reflect example in section 5.2 of MAP draft
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="FMR Option Example">
        <figure align="center" anchor="img-fmr-example"
                title="FMR Option Example">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
TODO: Reflect example in section 5.3 of MAP draft
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="DMR Option Example">
        <figure align="center" anchor="img-dmr-example"
                title="DMR Option Examples">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
TODO: Reflect example in section 5.4 of MAP draft
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is kindly requested to allocate the following DHCPv6 option
      codes: TBD1 for OPTION_MAP, TBD2 for OPTION_MAP_RULE, TBD3 for
      OPTION_MAP_DMR, and TBD4 for OPTION_MAP_PORTPARAMS. All values should be
      added to the DHCPv6 option code space defined in Section 24.3 of <xref
      target="RFC3315"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Implementation of this document does not present any new security
      issues, but as with all DHCPv6-derived configuration state, it is
      completely possible that the configuration is being delivered by a third
      party (Man In The Middle). As such, there is no basis to trust that the
      access over the MAP can be trusted, and it should not therefore bypass
      any security mechanisms such as IP firewalls.</t>

      <t>Readers concerned with security of MAP provisioning over DHCPv6 are
      encouraged to read <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dhc-secure-dhcpv6"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Section XX of <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref> discusses
      security issues of the MAP mechanism.</t>

      <t>Section 23 of <xref target="RFC3315"></xref> discusses DHCPv6-related
      security issues.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document was created as a product of a MAP design team.
      Following people were members of that team: Congxiao Bao, Mohamed
      Boucadair, Gang Chen, Maoke Chen, Wojciech Dec, Xiaohong Deng, Jouni
      Korhonen, Xing Li, Satoru Matsushima, Tomasz Mrugalski, Tetsuya
      Murakami, Jacni Qin, Necj Scoberne, Qiong Sun, Tina Tsou, Dan Wing, Leaf
      Yeh and Jan Zorz.</t>

      <t>Former MAP design team members are: Remi Despres.</t>

      <t>Authors would like to thank Bernie Volz for his insightful comments
      and suggestions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!--  SECTION 8.1:  Normative References		-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-map.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3633"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119" ?>
    </references>

    <!--  SECTION 8.2:  Informative References		-->

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226" ?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6335"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.mdt-softwire-map-deployment.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-homenet-arch"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-option-guidelines.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.mrugalski-dhc-dhcpv6-4rd.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.boucadair-dhcpv6-shared-address-option.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-secure-dhcpv6.xml" ?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.murakami-softwire-4rd.xml" ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
